[Music]
hundreds of millions of operations are
performed every year and the risk of
death is typically around a half a
percent
to which patients might say things like
i could just die as easily crossing the
road
making it clear they really don't
understand the difference
in magnitude of risk
one way to communicate risk is by
analogy for example just going under
anesthetic
carries about a one in a hundred
thousand chance you won't wake up
how much is that well that's about the
same risk as an expert skydive
okay but that still may be kind of hard
to wrap your head around it's hard to
think in terms of small numbers like
imagine discussing a seventeen ten
thousandths of a mile by twenty two
point seven ten thousands of a mile rug
like how big even is that
we need more digestible units enter the
micromort
as a unit of comparing and communicating
risk to patients
a micromort is a unit equivalent to a
one in a million chance of
dying one million is like the chances of
flipping a coin and getting 20 heads or
tails in a row
or a little less than the chances of
getting a royal flush
but the real utility is to help compare
different risks
to one another using the same metric
for example driving a hundred miles
entails about a one million chance of
death so that's one micro mort
scuba diving is like five micromorts per
dive so each dive is as risky as driving
500 miles
so now we have a way to directly compare
the risk of surgical procedures and
common activities so like giving birth
is as risky as driving from new york to
l.a and then back again
but getting a caesarean is more than
twice as risky even something like a
simple hernia repair carries the same
risk of dying is like skydiving 200
times
now obviously sometimes you have no
choice but death from varicose vein
surgery or circumcision could probably
be avoided
i was surprised to learn that regular
horseback riding is like four times
deadlier than rock climbing
but like getting chemo and radiation for
head and neck cancer is riskier than
rock climbing for 500 years
driving 5 million miles or jumping 5 000
skydives etc
one leading cause of death i really
didn't talk about and how not to die is
accidental death
we have approximately a 1 million chance
of dying just by accident every day of
our lives and about half of that risk is
dying in a car crash based on u.s
averages
then there's all sorts of other ways i'm
surprised to learn americans have about
a one in two hundred thousand chance
every year of dying from a foreign body
entering an orifice other than the mouth
other things we may want to avoid
include climbing mount everest about 30
times riskier than coal mining or base
jumping
trains and planes are actually
equivalent over the same distance but
riding a motorcycle is about 50 times
deadlier than riding in a car though
cycling to a destination is riskier too
about 10 times as deadly as driving in
the near term
here's a good example of how one can use
micro mort comparisons to help put
things in perspective
certain types of breast implants can
cause a rare type of cancer a type of
breast implant associated lymphoma
you can imagine how scary this is for
the millions of women who have implants
but check out the risk compared to the
risk of other common activities your
risk of dying from this kind of cancer
is less than a single day of skiing
now it's probably better to die quick on
the slopes and all the slow suffering of
cancer with the risk of bankrupting your
family but at least it can put the risk
of the implant cancer killing you
in context
[Music]
you